<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rich mans vvarning-peece A sermon, vpon occasion, formerly preached, and now published, by the author, Humfrey Sydenham, late fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118064</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853273</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853273</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18643</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13269)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18643)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1190:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rich mans vvarning-peece A sermon, vpon occasion, formerly preached, and now published, by the author, Humfrey Sydenham, late fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston [and William Stansby] for Nathanael Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Stansby printed quires C-F (STC).</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part of "Sermons by Humph. Sydenham" (STC 23572); the general title page for the latter was printed as F4 of this item.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18643:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18643:1"/>
            <p>THE RICH MANS WARNING-PEECE.</p>
            <p>A SERMON, VPON OCCASION, FORMERLY PREACHED, AND NOW publiſhed, by the Author, <hi>Humfrey Sydenham,</hi> late Fellow of Wadham Colledge in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Monendi ſunt diuites, qui tanta paticbantur pro auro, quanta erant ſuſtinenda pro Chriſto; inter tormenta, nemo Chriſtum confitendo, amiſit; Nemo aurum, niſi negando, ſeruauit; quocirca, vtiliora erant (fortaſſè) tormenta, quae bonum incorruptibile amandum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebant, quàm illa bona quae ſine vllo vtili fructu dominos ſui amore torquebant. <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug. lib. 1. de ciuit. Dei. cap. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Butter.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18643:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18643:2"/>
            <head>TO THE GREAT ORNAMENT OF HER SEX, AND NAME, MISTRIS ANNE PORTMAN, &amp;c. THE accumulation of <hi>Honours, here,</hi> and of <hi>Glory,</hi> in future.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My worthieſt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat you formerlie vouchſafed to peruſe in a rude <hi>tranſcript;</hi> J here preſent you in a character, like your ſelfe, and vertues, <hi>faire, and legible;</hi> J thinke it my <hi>prime honour,</hi> that it must now weare your <hi>liuery,</hi> and what ſhall immortall it, your <hi>name;</hi> Had it nothing elſe to make it liue in the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb facs="tcp:18643:3"/>and eſteeme of others, <hi>this</hi> were enough to giue it both <hi>countenance,</hi> and <hi>eternity;</hi> Greatneſſe can onely patronize our endeauours, Goodneſſe glorifies them. Vnder that ſtampe and ſeale of yours J haue aduentured it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, that you might know my reſpects are the <hi>ſame</hi> in publike, which they were, lately, vnder a priuate, though noble roofe; J neuer yet whiſpered an obſeruance, but J dar'd proclaime it to the world, and then, too, when there might be ſome pretence and colour to ſuſpect my loyalty; where I am engag'd once in my ſeruices, and profeſſe them, J am not beaten off by the cauſeleſſe diſtaſtes of thoſe J honour; you J euer did, and the <hi>name</hi> you beautifie; on which, though I am no longer an <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant,</hi> J am ſtill a <hi>votary,</hi> and ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:18643:3"/>a one, whoſe <hi>knee</hi> ſpeakes as loude for it, as his <hi>tongue;</hi> his deuotions, as his thanks; and both theſe from a heart ſwept ſo cleane of deceit, or falſehood, that could it lodge ſo much <hi>ſophiſtrie</hi> as to teach the <hi>lips</hi> to quauer, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, J had not been thus (perhaps) vnder the furrowes of a diſpleaſed brow, but might haue prooued as faire in the ſmile and cringe of many, as J am now <hi>downe the winde,</hi> both in their <hi>countenance,</hi> and <hi>opinion.</hi> But, <hi>ſinceritie</hi> is the <hi>ſame,</hi> ſtill, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>exile,</hi> or <hi>aduancement,</hi> in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, or honour; whereſoeuer I trauell J carry <hi>my ſelfe</hi> with me; I am not torne into <hi>diſtractions,</hi> and <hi>feares,</hi> not parcelled (as others) into <hi>doubtes,</hi> and <hi>hopes;</hi> but, where J am, J am in the <hi>whole man;</hi> and, where J am, <hi>ſo,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:18643:4"/>I am <hi>All</hi> yours; <hi>All</hi> in my <hi>morall, ciuill,</hi> and <hi>diuine</hi> obſeruances, one that will <hi>thanke</hi> you, <hi>honour</hi> you, and <hi>pray</hi> for you, vnfainedly, willingly, constantly, whileſt I am thought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the <hi>name,</hi> or <hi>attribute</hi> of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humbly-deuoted</hi> Humfry Sydenham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18643:4"/>
            <head>THE RICH MANS WARNING-PEECE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM. 62.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If Riches increaſe, ſet not thy Heart vpon them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Finde no <hi>diſpute</hi> here, about the <hi>title</hi> of this <hi>Pſalme;</hi> 'tis <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ds</hi> to <hi>Ieduthun;</hi> that <hi>Ieduthun</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho <hi>prophecied with the Harpe,</hi> and <hi>with Trumpets, and Cymballs, and loude inſtruments of Muſicke, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the Lord,</hi> 1. Chron. 16.42.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Theame</hi> and <hi>Subiect</hi> of it is <hi>various,</hi> and <hi>mixt;</hi> not ſet <hi>mournefully</hi> to <hi>ſtraines</hi> of <hi>penitence</hi> or <hi>mortality</hi> (as in others of his ſacred <hi>Anthems</hi>) but to <hi>Aiers</hi> of more ſpirit and life, ſuch as would ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limate and intraunce the <hi>Deuotion</hi> of the <hi>Hearer.</hi> The former part whereof is <hi>key'd</hi> high, <hi>very high,</hi> and reacheth <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>powerfull mercies;</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tun'd lower, to <hi>Man,</hi> and toucheth on his <hi>frailties</hi> and weake <hi>deportment.</hi> That which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18643:5"/>his <hi>God</hi> is (as 'twere) the <hi>plaine-ſong;</hi> the <hi>ground</hi> and <hi>burden</hi> of it <hi>graue,</hi> and <hi>ſober,</hi> but full of <hi>maieſty, My ſoule watteth vpon God, He is the Rocke of my Saluation and defence,</hi> at the ſecond verſe; but, <hi>The Rocke of my ſtrength, and Refuge,</hi> at the ſeuenth. That which concernes <hi>Man,</hi> is full of <hi>Deſcant,</hi> runnes <hi>nimbly</hi> on his <hi>ſtate, degrees, condition;</hi> diuides betweene the <hi>humble,</hi> and the <hi>proude,</hi> and cenſures <hi>both, Men of lowe degree are vanitie, and men of high degree are a lye,</hi> verſe 9. Thus hauing warbled ſweetly about the heart and middle of the <hi>Pſalme;</hi> at length he ſhuts vp his <hi>Harmony</hi> in <hi>Diſcord:</hi> In the front of this verſe <hi>He</hi> quarrels with the <hi>Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> and the <hi>Oppreſſor:</hi> and at the foote thereof (as if the <hi>Great Man</hi> were neere allied them) <hi>Hee</hi> throwes in a <hi>cauill</hi> concerning <hi>Riches;</hi> where <hi>He</hi> firſt, put's the <hi>caſe,</hi> with a <hi>ſi affluxerint, If Riches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe,</hi> then, the <hi>reſolution</hi> or <hi>aduice</hi> on it, <hi>nolite cor apponere, Set not your heart vpon them.</hi> Theſe are the parts, plainely, without <hi>violence,</hi> or <hi>affectation;</hi> ſo is the <hi>diſcourſe</hi> on them; in the deliuery of which, I muſt beg that double <hi>charitie</hi> which doth commonly encourage weake men in their ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours; <hi>Patrence, Attention:</hi> and firſt of the <hi>ſi affluxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, if Riches encreaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Riches</hi> haue carried their weight of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>eſteem</hi> through all <hi>Ages,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pats. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and, almoſt, all <hi>conditions</hi> in them; but not alwaies, at the ſame <hi>hught; Thoſe</hi> of our <hi>Fore-fathers</hi> lay moſt in their <hi>Flocks,</hi> and <hi>Droues;</hi> the <hi>Fold</hi> was their <hi>Treaſure-houſe,</hi> and not, the <hi>Tent.</hi> The word <hi>poecunia, money,</hi> was not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18643:5"/>
               <hi>then</hi> heard off, but <hi>Peculium, Gaine,</hi> which (as <hi>Viues</hi> notes it vpon <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) was firſt deriued from <hi>pecudes, Cattell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jn lib. <hi>7.</hi> de ciu Dei cap. <hi>12.</hi> Aug. etiam lib. de Domo diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plina cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> becauſe theſe were all the wealth of <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> for they were then (for the moſt part) <hi>Shepheards.</hi> The <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>reſpect</hi> of <hi>Riches</hi> were neere their <hi>Meridian</hi> in the daies of <hi>Solomon,</hi> when they firſt began to ſhine in their full <hi>luſtre;</hi> before a few <hi>Aſſes</hi> loaden with <hi>Lentiles</hi> and <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Corne,</hi> were thought a <hi>large preſent</hi> for a <hi>King; Then,</hi> multitudes of Camels, with <hi>Spices, gold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 10.2.</note> and <hi>precious ſtones</hi> ſcarce worth <hi>acceptance; Of old,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 10.27. Exod. 30.18.</note> a few <hi>ſhekels</hi> of <hi>ſiluer</hi> were a <hi>canonized</hi> treaſure; <hi>Now,</hi> they were of no <hi>repute,</hi> but <hi>as ſtones in the ſtreets of Ieruſalem.</hi> In fine,<note place="margin">1 King. 10.22.</note> 
               <hi>Lauers</hi> of <hi>braſſe</hi> were in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning rich enough for the <hi>Tabernacles</hi> of our <hi>God;</hi> but <hi>veſſels</hi> of <hi>beaten gold</hi> muſt be heere ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer'd, for the <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſels</hi> of a <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Riches</hi> are now at their <hi>high ſpring;</hi> euery <hi>Tide</hi> wafts in <hi>ſiluer,</hi> in ſhips of <hi>Tarſhiſh,</hi> and <hi>gold</hi> in the <hi>Nauy</hi> of <hi>Hiram; Treaſure</hi> flowes in that aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, that it doth no more <hi>ſatisfie,</hi> but <hi>amaze;</hi> a <hi>Queene</hi> beholds it, and there's <hi>no ſpirit in her.</hi> 1. Reg. 10.27. From <hi>amazement</hi> in this <hi>age,</hi> it growes to <hi>veneration</hi> in the next; that which was, <hi>erewhile,</hi> but an <hi>Ingot,</hi> or <hi>rude lumpe,</hi> is, <hi>Now,</hi> trick't vp into a <hi>Godhead Gold</hi> ſhall be no longer for <hi>vſe,</hi> or <hi>ornament,</hi> but for <hi>worſhip;</hi> and now the <hi>Nations</hi> begin to kneele to it, and giue it the <hi>deuoute posture</hi> of the <hi>whole man;</hi> the <hi>eleuation</hi> of the eye, and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panſion</hi> of the hands, and the <hi>Hoſanna</hi> of the tongue, and the <hi>Magnificat</hi> of the heart; and thus, in a <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18643:6"/>applauſe</hi> of their <hi>new-got Deity,</hi> the <hi>Cornet,</hi> the <hi>Flute,</hi> the <hi>Sackbut,</hi> the <hi>Pſaltery,</hi> and the <hi>Dulcimer</hi> ſhall ſound out their <hi>loude Idolatrie.</hi> Nay, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Romanes</hi> were growne ſo <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> to their <hi>maſſe</hi> of <hi>Treaſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>7.</hi> de ciu. Dei cap. <hi>12.</hi> &amp;, de diſcipl. Christ. tract. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>they</hi> made not onely <hi>money</hi> their <hi>God,</hi> but cal'd <hi>God, money;</hi> ſo their <hi>Iupiter</hi> was named <hi>pecunia,</hi> becauſe there was (as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectur'd) a kinde of <hi>omnipotency</hi> in <hi>money,</hi> which though it <hi>creates</hi> not, yet it <hi>commandeth</hi> all things. <hi>O magnam rationem Diuini nominis</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>hoc Auaritia Ioui nomen impoſuit: Auarice,</hi> no doubt, thus <hi>Chriſtned Iupiter,</hi> at firſt, that <hi>Thoſe</hi> which affected <hi>Coyne,</hi> ſhould not ſeeme to loue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ibid.</note> but the very <hi>King</hi> of gods. Had <hi>Hee</hi> been called <hi>Riches,</hi> the <hi>Title</hi> had been more <hi>paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi> and the <hi>deuotion</hi> leſſe <hi>ſottiſh;</hi> for, <hi>Diuitiae</hi> are one thing, and, <hi>Pecunia,</hi> another; we call the <hi>Good,</hi> and the <hi>Iuſt,</hi> and the <hi>Wiſe, Rich;</hi> which haue little, or nothing but in <hi>vertus;</hi> the <hi>Auaritious,</hi> and <hi>Gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, Poore;</hi> becauſe they euer want. Moreouer, <hi>God</hi> himſelfe we truly ſtile <hi>Rich;</hi> yet not, <hi>Pecunia,</hi> but, <hi>Omnipotentia;</hi> ſo ſaith the <hi>Father</hi> in his ſeuenth booke <hi>De Ciuitate Dei. cap.</hi> 12. And indeed, the <hi>God</hi> of our happineſſe wee ſtile <hi>Omnipotence,</hi> and not <hi>Money;</hi> but, ſometimes, to beautifie and ſet out his <hi>perfections, Riches.</hi> So we finde, <hi>Riches of his goodneſſe,</hi> Rom. 2. and <hi>Riches of his mercy,</hi> Rom. 9. and <hi>Riches of his grace,</hi> Epheſ. 2. and <hi>Riches of his wiſedome,</hi> Rom. 11. Loe, his <hi>Goodneſſe, Grace, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Wiſedome,</hi> and to ſhew their <hi>Height,</hi> and <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and <hi>Immenſitie,</hi> and <hi>Euer laſtingneſſe</hi> no thing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18643:6"/>to expreſſe them, but <hi>Riches;</hi> which, if they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord ſuch glory in the <hi>Metaphor,</hi> no doubt, there is ſomething of <hi>worth</hi> and <hi>eſtimation</hi> in the <hi>letter,</hi> too; <hi>Riches,</hi> as they are <hi>Riches,</hi> haue both their <hi>vertue</hi> and <hi>applauſe;</hi> for the <hi>Spirit</hi> calls them <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,</hi> and <hi>Good things;</hi> but they are <hi>externa media, Good things without vs,</hi> which we may, <hi>vti,</hi> not <hi>frui, vſe</hi> onely, not <hi>enioy,</hi> or rather not <hi>ioy in them;</hi> if <hi>Delight,</hi> here, be not more proper then <hi>Ioye;</hi> ſince <hi>Ioye</hi> (for the moſt part) <hi>poynts</hi> to things <hi>Spirituall; Delight,</hi> to pleaſures <hi>Temporall.</hi> Howeuer, <hi>Riches</hi> may ſometimes lawfully <hi>touch,</hi> both with our <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> and <hi>Deſire,</hi> ſo the <hi>Ayme</hi> be not prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and oblique; either, to make them as <hi>Fuell</hi> for our <hi>Pride,</hi> or <hi>Bellowes</hi> for our <hi>Luſt,</hi> or <hi>Oyle</hi> for our <hi>Concupiſcence,</hi> or <hi>Flames</hi> for our <hi>Ambition,</hi> or <hi>Smoake</hi> for our <hi>Vncharitableneſſe.</hi> For though mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Beneficence</hi> and <hi>gift</hi> looke towards <hi>Riches,</hi> as their <hi>Source,</hi> and <hi>Inſtrumentall cauſe;</hi> yet, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, where there is moſt of <hi>Fortune,</hi> there is leaſt of <hi>Charity,</hi> and ſo when there is <hi>Abilitie</hi> of <hi>Diſtribution,</hi> there wants <hi>Will;</hi> and that euer ſtrangles the <hi>Nobleneſſe</hi> of <hi>Thoſe</hi> which are to giue, and the <hi>ſhoutes</hi> and <hi>Bencdictions</hi> of them which ſhould receiue. And this, I beleeue, firſt gaue life and breathing to that grey-hair'd <hi>para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox: Si opes ſint bona cur non reddunt poſsidentes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos?</hi> If <hi>Riches</hi> be <hi>good,</hi> why haue they not influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence into him that ownes them, and ſo make the poſſeſſor <hi>good? Soule</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Rich man</hi> in the <hi>Parable</hi>) <hi>Thou haſt much good, laid vp for many yeeres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 12.</note>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18643:7"/>
               <hi>ſleepe and take thine eaſe;</hi> marke the <hi>Paraphraſe. Quid eſt iniquius homine, qui multa bona vult habere, &amp; bonus ipſe eſſe non vult? Indignus es qui habeas, qui non vis eſſe, quod vis habere:</hi> The Father in his 28. Sermon <hi>de Diuerſis.</hi> What a <hi>maſſe</hi> of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie is man ſwolne vnto, that ſtill deſires much <hi>good,</hi> yet not to be <hi>good</hi> himſelfe? He is vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to <hi>haue</hi> any thing that he might <hi>Bee,</hi> which would not <hi>bee</hi> what he would <hi>haue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Riches</hi> therefore, though they challenge the <hi>Name</hi> of good, yet there are ſuch, as both <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Bad</hi> doe indifferently inherit, and whileſt they are good, cannot denominate their <hi>Maſter</hi> good; and therefore to rectifie this obliquitie, Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> acquaints vs with a <hi>Two-fold Good; Bonum quod facit bonum,</hi> and <hi>Bonum vndè fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cias bonum:</hi> There is a <hi>Good</hi> which doth make <hi>good,</hi> and that's thy <hi>God,</hi> and there is a <hi>Good</hi> by which thou maieſt doe <hi>good,</hi> and that's thy <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> Doe good; how? Hearke, the <hi>Pſalmist; He hath diſperſed abroad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 1 12.</note> 
               <hi>He hath giuen to the poore, his righteouſneſſe endureth for euer,</hi> Pſalme 112.9. <hi>Hoc eſt Bonum, hoc est bonum vndè ſis Iuſtitiâ bonus; ſi habeas bonum vndè ſis bonus fac bonum de bono, vndè non es bonus:</hi> So the <hi>Father</hi> warbles, in his third Sermon <hi>de verbis Domini.</hi> Behold, thou haſt large heapes of <hi>Treaſure;</hi> diſtribute them; in ſo doing, thou doſt inlarge thy happineſſe; <hi>Heere</hi> is but giuing to the <hi>Poore;</hi> and then, <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe for euer.</hi> Loe, an exchange of infinite ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage; weigh thy <hi>Disburſements</hi> with thy <hi>Gaine,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18643:7"/>thy <hi>Diminutions</hi> with thy <hi>Encreaſe;</hi> thy <hi>ſtore,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, is ſomewhat thinner, but thy <hi>Iustice</hi> is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haune'd; That onely is leſſened which thou wert ſhortly to loſe; and this improoued which thou art euer to poſſeſſe. In fine, there is onely a <hi>Diſperſit,</hi> or a <hi>Dedit,</hi> in reſpect of the gift; <hi>he hath diſpoſed, or giuen;</hi> no more; but there is a <hi>Manet in aeternum:</hi> for the <hi>Reward</hi> of the giuer, <hi>His Righte-ouſneſſe endureth for euer;</hi> for euer, why? The <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> anſwereth, <hi>He that hath charity hath God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn 4</note> 
               <hi>God dwels in him, and He in God:</hi> and where <hi>God</hi> dwels, there muſt needs be a <hi>Manet in aeternum;</hi> for <hi>God</hi> is <hi>eternity.</hi> A <hi>Rich man,</hi> then, if he haue not <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> what hath he? And a <hi>Poore man</hi> if he haue <hi>Charity,</hi> what hath he not? <hi>Tu fortè putas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ſerm. <hi>64.</hi> de Temp.</note> 
               <hi>quod ille ſit diues cuius Arca plena eſt Auro, &amp; ille non eſt diues cuius conſcientia plena eſt Deo:</hi> Thou thinkeſt, perchance, that <hi>Hee</hi> is <hi>Rich,</hi> whoſe cheſts are throng'd with gold, and he not <hi>Rich,</hi> whoſe <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> is fil'd with God; But the <hi>Father</hi> puts the <hi>Lye</hi> vpon this foule miſpriſion with an <hi>Ille vere Diues, in quo Deus habitare dignatur,</hi> in his 64. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>de tempore. Hee</hi> is truely <hi>Rich</hi> in whom <hi>God</hi> hath vouchſafed to dwell, for <hi>There</hi> is <hi>Sacietie,</hi> and full content, <hi>Metell is</hi> or <hi>Croeſus</hi> not halfe ſo rich; and <hi>He</hi> truly <hi>poore,</hi> in whom God hath refaied to dwell, for <hi>There</hi> is nothing but <hi>Anxiety</hi> and lamentable Indigence, <hi>Regulus,</hi> or <hi>Irus,</hi> not halfe ſo poore. <hi>Quite, &amp; alia nouit, non propter illa bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior, ſed propter te ſolum beatus.</hi> The ſame Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> in the third of his <hi>Confeſsions, cap.</hi> 4.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18643:8"/>
            <p>How miſerable then is the condition of thoſe who ſuffer the <hi>current</hi> of their <hi>Affections</hi> to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinately carried from the euer-ſpringing foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines <hi>aboue,</hi> vpon <hi>broken Ciſternes</hi> that will hold no water? From the <hi>Creator</hi> of the world, to <hi>Creatures</hi> heere, of ouer-valued, and falſe <hi>eſteeme,</hi> a little <hi>Idolatriz'd Earth,</hi> or <hi>magnified traſh;</hi> a few gariſh <hi>Tranſitories, Riches</hi> but improperly, for they haue neither <hi>Truth,</hi> nor <hi>Certaintie;</hi> their <hi>worth</hi> is lame, and crutched meerely vpon opinion; their <hi>luſtre</hi> counterfeit, like thoſe falſe lights which delude the wandring <hi>Sea-men;</hi> and betray them to ſhelues and rockes, where both their <hi>Hopes,</hi> and they, are vntimely ſplit. But ſuppoſe thoſe <hi>Riches</hi> (as I ſuppoſe onely) to be as true, as thoſe <hi>Lights</hi> are falſe; yet thus to indulge them is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous <hi>Idolatry,</hi> ſince that which is ordained for a <hi>Seruant,</hi> they make not onely their <hi>Maſter,</hi> but their <hi>God.</hi> And indeed, <hi>Such</hi> may be ſaid to haue <hi>Riches</hi> as we are ſaid to haue the <hi>Feauer,</hi> when the <hi>Feauer</hi> hath vs;<note place="margin">Sen. ep. <hi>78.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>They</hi> haue not <hi>Riches,</hi> but <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> them; for <hi>They</hi> which are either tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their <hi>glory,</hi> or rapt with their <hi>poſſeſsions,</hi> doe by <hi>Riches</hi> as birds doe by <hi>Daring-glaſſes, play with their owne ruine;</hi> how euer, ſuch are their faire <hi>allurements</hi> and <hi>inuitations,</hi> that <hi>Thoſe</hi> who are onely taken with the <hi>outſide,</hi> and <hi>Barke</hi> of things, are ſtrangely infatuated: but in this, <hi>They</hi> reſemble little Children, which valew e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery painted trifle, as a <hi>Treaſure;</hi> a <hi>Bugle,</hi> or glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie <hi>Carkanet,</hi> as precious as that of <hi>Onyx.</hi> And
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18643:8"/>what difference is there (ſaith the <hi>Stoicke</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them and vs, <hi>Niſi quod nos circa tabulas &amp; ſtatuas inſanimus, charius inepti,</hi> wee are mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding after <hi>Statues,</hi> and <hi>Pillars,</hi> more coftly fooliſh, <hi>Illos, reperti in littore calculi leues, &amp; aliquid haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis varietatis, delectant,</hi> they taken with <hi>ſtones</hi> and <hi>ſhells</hi> of various colours, found on the <hi>Sea</hi>-ſhore;<note place="margin">Sen. Ep. <hi>119.</hi>
               </note> we, with <hi>pillars</hi> of <hi>Iaſper,</hi> and <hi>Porphirie,</hi> from the <hi>Sands</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> or <hi>Deſerts</hi> of <hi>Affrica,</hi> to ſhoulder ſome <hi>Porch,</hi> or <hi>Dyning-roome,</hi> to banquet or <hi>reuell</hi> in. All this Equipage of <hi>Greatnes</hi> is but a <hi>Glorious vanity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. vt ſupra.</note> and that which the <hi>Moraliſt</hi> call's <hi>Bracteata foelicitas,</hi> a ſpangled happines, a leafe of gold laid on <hi>Iron,</hi> which for a time glitter's, and then ruſt's; a gaudie Vane, or Streamer on the top of ſome <hi>Turret,</hi> whiuer's and flicker's with euery blaſt; a quaint <hi>Iewell,</hi> hung looſe in haire, which, as it dangle's, fall's; a verie <hi>Glaſſie Pompe, cùm ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det, frangitur;</hi> like <hi>Bubbles,</hi> which in their ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, breake; Flattering and deluding <hi>Bleſſings,</hi> and ſuch as proue better to them that hope for them, then to thoſe that doe enioy them; For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of that <hi>Contentment</hi> which ſhould aſſaile them by the fruition of their deſires, here is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Calamity,</hi> &amp; new torment; Care of their preſeruation, and doubt of their diſpoſall, and feare of their loſſe, and trouble of their improue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; to theſe, <hi>leane watchfulnes,</hi> broken thoughts, hollow reſolutions, interrupted peace, beſides a whole <hi>Hoaſt</hi> of ſelfe-vexations and) the <hi>wheele</hi> the <hi>Racke</hi> not halfe the <hi>Torture.</hi> Thus, <hi>Gold</hi> is a <hi>ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-Blocke</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:18643:9"/>to him that doth ſacrifice vnto it, and very fooles ſhall bee taken with it, (ſaith <hi>Ieſus</hi> the ſon of <hi>Sirach</hi>) ſhall be taken with it? nay, ſhall be taken from it, euen when he doth ſacrifice vnto it; ſo ſaith <hi>Ieſus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Dauid, Foole, this night ſhall thy ſoule be taken from thee,</hi> taken from thee, two wayes; Firſt, thy ſoule from the riches of thy bodie, and then thy ſoule from the bodie of thy riches; And therefore, there is a <hi>vae Diuitibus,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt ſuch,<note place="margin">Amos 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>Woe to you that are at eaſe in Sion, and truſt in the mountaines of Samar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which, though the <hi>Marcionite</hi> would make a <hi>vae,</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Admonition,</hi> and not of <hi>Malediction;</hi> yet, <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in the chaſticement of that error, ſaith; that a <hi>Canete</hi> is alwayes vſed in matters of <hi>Aduice,</hi> but a <hi>vae</hi> neuer, but in thoſe thunder-claps of <hi>fury</hi> and <hi>malediction.</hi> So, we find only a <hi>Cauete</hi> againſt <hi>Auarice,</hi> becauſe <hi>That</hi> is the <hi>Semen,</hi> and firſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (as 'twere) of <hi>Riches, Beware of Coueteouſneſſe, for mans life conſiſteth not in Abundance. Luke</hi> 12.13. But there is a fearefull <hi>vae</hi> againſt <hi>Riches,</hi> as though they ſtill cryed for diuine <hi>Caſtigations, Woe vnto you that are rich,</hi> why? <hi>you haue receiued your conſolation, Luke</hi> 6.24. your conſolation, how? <hi>Ex Diuitijs, de gloria illarum, &amp; ſecularibus fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> of your riches, and their glory, and all ſecular content, not otherwiſe. So ſaith the Father in his fourth Booke againſt <hi>Marcion. Cap.</hi> 5. What folly iſt then to purſue that with violence and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> which when wee haue gain'd is no <hi>ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction,</hi> but a <hi>torment?</hi> what madnes thus to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerate
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18643:9"/>and crucifie the whole man for a few titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and opinionated <hi>riches;</hi> of which hee that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſe's and drinke's deepeſt is euer thirſtie? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing quenches an immoderate appetite, <hi>poculum reſpuit, quia fluutum ſitit</hi> (aith <hi>Augustine</hi>) <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racts</hi> and riuers are but draughts competent for ſuch concopiſcences to ſwallow <hi>Habes Aurum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes Argentum, concupiſcis aurnm, concupiſcis ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentum, &amp; Habes, &amp; concupiſcis, &amp; plenus es, &amp; ſitis; morbus est non opulentia,</hi> the ſame Father in his 3. Sermon <hi>de verbis Apoſtoli.</hi> How miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are thoſe deſires, which are not bounded by what wee doe poſſeſſe, but by what wee can atchieue. If a man ſuppoſe that <hi>Fortune</hi> hee is <hi>Lord</hi> of, not voluminous enough, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee be <hi>Monarch</hi> of the whole world; yet is hee wretched: <hi>hee is not happie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. lib de paupertate</note> 
               <hi>that thinks himſelfe happie;</hi> hee that agreeth well with his pouertie is a rich man, and hee that agreeth not well with his riches is a poore man; hee is not rich that ſtill lack's ſomething, nor he poore that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing, <hi>vtrum maius habere multum, an ſatis,</hi> 'tis the Sto cks <hi>Dilemma;</hi> whether had'ſt thou rather to haue <hi>much,</hi> or <hi>enough?</hi> hee that hath <hi>much,</hi> deſires more, which is an argument, hee hath not yet <hi>ſufficient;</hi> he that hath <hi>enough,</hi> hath obtain'd the <hi>end,</hi> which neuer befals a <hi>rich man. Seneca</hi> labour's to preſſe this home to his <hi>Lucillius;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep <hi>119.</hi>
               </note> Set before me the reputed rich, <hi>Craſſus,</hi> or <hi>Lucini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> let him calculate his full <hi>Reuenewes,</hi> what hee hath in preſent, and hoped for <hi>Poſſeſſions;</hi> this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18643:10"/>man (if thou beleeue me) is poore; or (if thy ſelfe) may bee poore; whether is hee <hi>Couetous,</hi> or <hi>Prodigall?</hi> if <hi>Couetous,</hi> he hath nothing; if <hi>Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall,</hi> he ſhall haue nothing; The <hi>Gold</hi> thou cal'ſt his, is but his <hi>Cabonet's, Et Quis Aerario inuidet?</hi> who would enuy a full coffer? The man whom thou ſuppoſe'ſt to be <hi>Maſter</hi> of his treaſure, is but the bagge that ſhut's it vp.</p>
            <p>Loe then, the baſe <hi>Idolatry</hi> of theſe times, and men, which not onely raiſe their <hi>Hecatombs</hi> to their <hi>Golden Saint,</hi> but <hi>Deifie</hi> the very <hi>Shrine</hi> that keepe's it, A peece of <hi>wrinckled prouidence,</hi> or <hi>gray hayr'd thrift;</hi> nay worſe, a meere <hi>decrepit Auarice;</hi> when for a little languiſhing and bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid <hi>Charitie,</hi> they embalme the <hi>Honours</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory</hi> of rich men with their precious <hi>Perfumes</hi> and <hi>Oyntments,</hi> ſuch as ſhould caſt only their Odours on the <hi>Monuments</hi> of <hi>good men;</hi> And not onely ſo, but they aduance their <hi>Statues</hi> and <hi>Pillars</hi> in our very <hi>Temples,</hi> I know not, whether more to the diſhonour of our God, or to the <hi>Immortalitie</hi> of their owne <hi>Name.</hi> What's this but to turne Iſraelite againe, and take off from the glory of the <hi>Lord of Hoaſts,</hi> to worſhip a <hi>Golden Calfe?</hi> By the Law of <hi>Nature</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Epicure</hi>) <hi>the greateſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are but a compos'd pouertie,</hi> and by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the greateſt <hi>pouertie</hi> is but <hi>ill-compos'd ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches;</hi> for he that pile's them by <hi>fraud</hi> or <hi>violence,</hi> builds Aauarice one ſtorie higher, to <hi>oppreſſion;</hi> and then not onely <hi>Pouerty,</hi> but <hi>Iudgement</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes; <hi>God ſhall raine ſnares vpon them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 18</note> That
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18643:10"/>which ſhould otherwiſe cheriſh, ſhall now intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle them; and then, <hi>Storme and Tempeſt ſhall bee their portion to drinke,</hi> ſuch a ſtorme as will not be allaid without a ſhower of vengeance. Hearke, how it blowe's? <hi>Woe vnto them, That ioyne Houſe to houſe, and lay field to field, till they be placed alone in the middeſt of the Earth; This is in mine eares; ſaith the Lord of Hoasts; of a truth, many houſes ſhall be deſolate, euen great and faire without an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant; Ten Acres of vineyard ſhall yeeld one Bath, and the ſeed of an Omer ſhall yeeld an Ephah:</hi> Is this all? No, the <hi>Thunder clap</hi> is behind, <hi>Hell hath enlarged her ſelfe, and opened her mouth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meaſure, and their multitude and their Pompe ſhall deſcend into it. Eſay</hi> 5.14. There is no <hi>miſery</hi> to vniuſt riches; no <hi>leanneſſe</hi> of <hi>teeth</hi> like <hi>thoſe</hi> which grow fat with the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of another; but, to them which <hi>grind Pouertie</hi> by <hi>Extortion, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorant plebem, ſicut eſcam panis, eate vp my people, as a morſell of bread,</hi> what <hi>Hell,</hi> here? what <hi>Horror</hi> in after times? Oh, the fearefull Eiulations ſome haue ſhrik'd! <hi>Would God had giuen me a heart ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe like the flint in the rockes of ſtone;</hi> which, as it can taſt no pleaſure, ſo no <hi>Torment;</hi> no torment, here; but, when <hi>the Heauens ſhall ſhriuell like a ſcroule, and the Hills moue like frighted men out of their place,</hi> what <hi>Mountaine</hi> ſhall they get by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty to fall vpon them? what couert to hide them from that fury, which they ſhall neuer bee able to <hi>ſuffer,</hi> nor <hi>auoide? Iudgements</hi> doe not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way follow <hi>Crimes</hi> as <hi>Thunder</hi> doth <hi>Lightening,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18643:11"/>Inſtantly; but, ſometimes, an <hi>Age</hi> is interpos'd, as betweene two <hi>Earth-quakes;</hi> though they may eſcape the darts and wounds of temporall <hi>perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> heere, yet the <hi>ſting</hi> that lie's behind is <hi>Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. They ſhall ſucke the Gall of Aſpes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 20.14.</note> 
               <hi>and the Vipers tongue ſhall ſlay them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, wee ſee, <hi>Riches</hi> and <hi>Bleſſedneſſe</hi> doe not alwayes <hi>kiſſe; He's</hi> not euer <hi>Happie</hi> that is <hi>proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous;</hi> the acquiſition of much wealth, is no <hi>End</hi> of miſerie, but a <hi>change:</hi> the <hi>Low-built Fortune</hi> har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's as much <hi>Peace,</hi> as that which is <hi>Higher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roof'd;</hi> and hath one aduantage beyond it, 'tis leſſe <hi>wind-ſhooke.</hi> The humble <hi>Hyſope</hi> and <hi>Shrub</hi> of the <hi>valley</hi> are not ſo expos'd to <hi>Tempeſts,</hi> as the <hi>Cedar in Libanus,</hi> or the <hi>Oke in Baſan;</hi> they are threatned with many a <hi>Cloud</hi> and <hi>Exhalation,</hi> which the other neither <hi>Feare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epicurus.</note> nor <hi>Suffer. Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Pouertie</hi> (ſaith the good <hi>Athenian</hi>) is an <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest thing;</hi> but 'tis no more <hi>Pouertie</hi> if it bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; we cannot ſay, hee is poore that is ſatisfied, but he that couet's more. <hi>He</hi> that is at peace with his deſires, and can compoſe himſelfe to what <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> only requires from him, is not only without the <hi>Senſe,</hi> but without the <hi>Feare</hi> of miſerie; is he poore that hath neither <hi>Gold,</hi> nor <hi>Hunger,</hi> nor <hi>Thirſt? plùs</hi> Iupiter <hi>nòn habet. Iupiter</hi> himſelfe hath no more; That is not <hi>little</hi> which is <hi>enough,</hi> nor that <hi>much</hi> which is <hi>not enough; He</hi> that think's <hi>much Little,</hi> is ſtill <hi>poore;</hi> and he that think's <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle much,</hi> is euer <hi>Rich; Rich</hi> in reſpect of Nature, though not <hi>Opinion.</hi> The man thou cal'ſt poore,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18643:11"/>hath, doubtleſſe, ſomething that is ſuperfluous; and where <hi>Superfluitie</hi> is, there can bee no want; where no want, no pouertie; on the otherſide, the man thou ſtil'ſt <hi>Rich,</hi> is either <hi>Poore,</hi> or <hi>like</hi> a poore man; he cannot improue his <hi>Store</hi> but by <hi>Fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie;</hi> and Frugalitie is but <hi>paupertas voluntaria,</hi> a voluntarie pouertie, <hi>Seneca</hi> call's it ſo in his fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Epiſtle <hi>ad Lucillium.</hi> Let's, then,<note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>91<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> borrow <hi>Aduice</hi> from that <hi>ſacred Heathen</hi> (pardon the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pethite, Seneca</hi> will owne it) and preſſe it home to the practice of a <hi>Christian, Meaſure all things by naturall deſires; only,</hi> beware thou mixe not <hi>Vices</hi> with <hi>Deſires; Nature</hi> content's her ſelfe with a little, what is, <hi>beyond,</hi> or <hi>aboue</hi> that, is impertinent, and not neceſſarie. Thou art <hi>hungrie,</hi> reach not after <hi>Dainties,</hi> the <hi>Appetite</hi> ſhall make that tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, <hi>which is next,</hi> whether thy <hi>bread</hi> be white, or browne, <hi>Nature</hi> queſtion's not. <hi>Illa ventrem nòn delectari vult, ſed impleri. She</hi> would haue the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die <hi>fed,</hi> not <hi>delighted.</hi> Thou art <hi>drie;</hi> whether this <hi>water</hi> runne from the next Lake, or that which is <hi>arted</hi> by Snow, or <hi>forraine</hi> cold, <hi>Nature</hi> diſputes not; <hi>ſhe</hi> labour's to quench thy <hi>Thirſt,</hi> not to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thy <hi>Palate,</hi> whether the cup be <hi>Gold,</hi> or <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall, Sabinian,</hi> or that of <hi>Murrha,</hi> or elſe the hollow of thine owne hand, it matter's not; Fixe thine eyes vpon the <hi>End</hi> of all things, &amp; thou wilt loath <hi>Superfluities: Nùm tibi cùm fauces vrit ſitis Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea quaeris pocula? Nùm eſuriens, faſtidis omnia praeter pauonem? Hunger</hi> is not <hi>Ambitious, ſhee</hi> looke's not after the <hi>qualitie</hi> of meates, but the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18643:12"/>
               <hi>meaſure;</hi> how ſhee may <hi>Fill</hi> the bodie, not <hi>pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> it; Theſe are torments of an vnhappie <hi>Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> when wee <hi>ſeeke</hi> new wayes how to <hi>prouoke,</hi> and <hi>glut</hi> the <hi>Appetite,</hi> and not only to <hi>refreſh</hi> our <hi>Tabernacles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus 37.</note> but to <hi>cloy</hi> them. <hi>Delicates powred vpon a mouth ſhut vp are like meſſes of meate ſet vpon a graue,</hi> things only for <hi>Spectacle,</hi> not <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt.</hi> Of all <hi>Gluttonies,</hi> that of the <hi>Eye</hi> is moſt <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curicall,</hi> when it would ſtill <hi>ſee Dainties</hi> which it cannot <hi>taſte,</hi> till the <hi>Deſire</hi> hath as much ſurfeited, as the <hi>Bodie,</hi> and ſo we abuſe the <hi>Bountie</hi> of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Nature</hi> to ſatisfie the <hi>Lust</hi> and <hi>Concupiſeence</hi> of the whole man; and this <hi>Rapine</hi> and greedineſſe of the <hi>ſence,</hi> is as vnwarrantable, as that of <hi>fortune,</hi> which breake's downe all bankes of <hi>moderation;</hi> and therefore, without either <hi>Morall</hi> or <hi>Diuine</hi> preſcription. There can be no <hi>Vertue in Extreme; no good, which conſiſt's not in exactneſſe of propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſo that by the <hi>diminution</hi> or <hi>exceſſe</hi> of that proportion, <hi>Vice</hi> inſinuates; inſomuch, that in the exuberancie of theſe outward creatures, <hi>Sinne</hi> is conceiued,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2.2. <hi>q.</hi> 118. <hi>Art.</hi> 1.</note> a <hi>Capitall,</hi> and <hi>Daring</hi> ſinne, when aboue a due equalitie, and meaſure, we either <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire</hi> or <hi>retaine</hi> them eagerly; And this the <hi>Schoole-man</hi> call's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an <hi>Immoderate</hi> hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and <hi>perſuite</hi> of temporals, in <hi>ſecunda ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae</hi> 118. <hi>quaest. Art.</hi> 1. There is no outward ſtate of life ſo bleſſed as that which Diuide's betweene <hi>Penurie</hi> and <hi>Abundance;</hi> the extreame on either ſide is <hi>Miſerie.</hi> And therefore the wiſeſt <hi>King</hi> that euer was, and the greateſt both for <hi>Treaſure</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:18643:12"/>and <hi>Retinue,</hi> in his owne deſire of ſecular things euer mixt his <hi>Oriſons</hi> with this <hi>Petition, Lord giue me neither Riches nor Pouertie, Sed victui meo tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bue neceſſaria, Feed mee with food conuenient</hi> (the <hi>Engliſh</hi> giue's it) but the <hi>Latine, neceſſarium,</hi> is more <hi>Emphaticall;</hi> there are ſome things <hi>Conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient</hi> for the Maieſtie of a <hi>King,</hi> which are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <hi>Neceſſary</hi> for his perſon; but <hi>Salomon,</hi> here, deſire's only to haue <hi>Nature</hi> accommodated, and not <hi>State; Riches</hi> he would haue none; and theſe are <hi>conuenient</hi> for him as a King, but ſomething to feed him with, and that is <hi>neceſſarie</hi> for him as a <hi>Man;</hi> an humble requeſt for ſo mightie a <hi>Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,</hi> and yet ſo much as he need's to beg, though, not ſo much as God hath purpos'd to beſtow; his <hi>Bleſsings</hi> come oftentimes in ſhowers when they are ſued for but as ſprinklings. In that exquiſite plat-forme and rule of Prayer preſcribed vs by our Sauiour, all temporall defires are inuolu'd in this, <hi>Giue vs this day our daily bread,</hi> 'tis <hi>Bread,</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wee aske, and bread only, for <hi>a day,</hi> and theſe are <hi>Both neceſſarie;</hi> Neceſſary two wayes; Firſt, in reſpect of <hi>our ſelues,</hi> for <hi>Bread</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt</hi>) <hi>ſtrengthen's the heart of Man;</hi> man's chiefeſt part, the <hi>Heart;</hi> and that chiefe part, fraile; and frailtie needs ſtrengthning euery day; Then, in reſpect of the <hi>command;</hi> it muſt be <hi>Bread,</hi> for a <hi>day,</hi> too; The <hi>Lord</hi> bidd's the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> gather <hi>Manna,</hi> only for <hi>a day,</hi> and the <hi>Goſpell</hi> enioynes the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> with a <hi>Nolite cogitare in craſtinum, Care not for to morrow, but let to morrow care for it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18643:13"/>ſelfe. Meritò ergò Chriſti Diſcipulus victum ſibi in Diem poſtulat, qui de craſtino cogitare prohibetur;</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyp de Orat. Dom.</note> Hee rightly demand's bread only for <hi>a day,</hi> who is forbid to prouide any thing for <hi>to morrow. I came naked out of my mothers wombe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob</hi>) <hi>and naked ſhall I returne. Wee brought nothing into this world</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>and nothing we ſhall carrie out; Nakedneſſe?</hi> and <hi>Nothing? into</hi> the world? and <hi>out</hi> of it? What then can we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire heere, but <hi>Neceſſaries?</hi> and what theſe are, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> giue's in two words, <hi>Victum, Tegu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, Food and Raiment,</hi> and enioyne's <hi>Content</hi> with theſe, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.8. But what food, what rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt wee be contented with? <hi>Neceſſarium victum, Neceſſarium tegumentum, nòn inane, nòn ſuperfluum,</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reſolue's in his fifth Sermon, <hi>De verbis Apoſtoli,</hi> Food and Raiment neceſſarie, not <hi>Luxurient,</hi> not <hi>Superfluous; Nature</hi> require's not the <hi>Latter,</hi> but if <hi>God</hi> ſometimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow them, make thoſe <hi>Superfluities</hi> another's <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, Sint tua ſuperflua pauperibus neceſſaria;</hi> 'tis the ſame <hi>Father's</hi> aduice in the ſame Sermon. Miſtake me not; I am no <hi>Diſciple</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor <hi>Athens,</hi> no <hi>Stoicke</hi> I, nor <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> I hate a <hi>Cloiſter,</hi> or a <hi>Stoa;</hi> I like not the Monke in his <hi>Monasterie,</hi> nor the <hi>Cynicke</hi> in his <hi>Tub,</hi> nor the <hi>Anchore:</hi> in his <hi>Cell;</hi> I loath the <hi>Penitentiarie</hi> and his <hi>water,</hi> the <hi>Capuchin</hi> and his <hi>Stonie Pillow;</hi> I pitie the thred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare <hi>Mendicant,</hi> and the bare-footed <hi>Pilgrime;</hi> ſuch wilfull penancing of the body (for ought I reade) God neither command's nor approue's. A
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18643:13"/>voluntarie retirement from <hi>Societie,</hi> or <hi>Fortune</hi> ſauour's more of <hi>Will,</hi> then <hi>Iudgement,</hi> of peeuiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then <hi>Religion.</hi> If <hi>God</hi> ſend me <hi>Riches</hi> I accept them thank fully, and imploy them, in my beſt, to <hi>his</hi> ſeruice, and <hi>mine owne;</hi> But if by <hi>Caſualtie,</hi> or <hi>Affliction,</hi> or ſome <hi>vnhappie Accident,</hi> I am driuen to <hi>Indigence,</hi> or <hi>Calamitie;</hi> or elſe, if <hi>God</hi> haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion'd mee ſuch an humble <hi>Condition;</hi> Ile take no indirect courſe to any higher, but carrie this <hi>cheerefully,</hi> without <hi>Solitarineſſe,</hi> or <hi>Diſcontent;</hi> and, as with the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of old <hi>Attalus,</hi> ſo with his <hi>Language</hi> too, <hi>Torqueor, ſed fortitèr, benè eſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. Epiſt. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>occidor, ſed fortitèr, beuè est.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And hence, (no doubt) it was, that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſo magnified his <hi>Paulinus;</hi> who hauing fallen from infinite <hi>riches</hi> to a retired <hi>pouertie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug lib. de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Det, cap <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> when the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians</hi> beſieged <hi>Nota</hi> (of which hee was <hi>Biſhop</hi>) ſpoiling all as they went, as a generall Deluge, and making him priſoner both to <hi>ſhame,</hi> and <hi>want,</hi> thus powr'd-out his deuout expreſſions to his <hi>God, Domine non excrucior propter Aurum, &amp;c.</hi> Lord, I am not troubled for <hi>gold,</hi> or <hi>ſiluer;</hi> for where all my treaſures are, thou knoweſt: euen there had he repos'd all his, where <hi>Hee</hi> aduis'd to lay them, who foretold theſe miſeries to fall vpon the world. A braue reſolution, and worthy of that <hi>Crowne,</hi> which wreathe's all <hi>Martyrdomes;</hi> and yet but ſuch as wee, out of the honour of our <hi>Profeſsion,</hi> ſhould haue, and, in our fires of <hi>Treall,</hi> ought to vſe. That <hi>Chriſtian</hi> who hath ſometimes ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>d in the glory of outward <hi>Fortunes,</hi> and afterwards
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18643:14"/>endur'd the <hi>Batteries</hi> of ſome temporall afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and yet in the mid'ſt of theſe cannot awake his <hi>Harpe,</hi> and <hi>Pſalterie,</hi> and ſing with <hi>Dauid, My heart O God is fixed, my heart is fixed, I will giue praiſe, Praiſe,</hi> aſwell for thy <hi>puniſhments,</hi> as thy <hi>Bleſsings,</hi> is a very <hi>Coward</hi> in temptation, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy either of his <hi>Conntenance,</hi> or <hi>Colours;</hi> Hee that cannot take vp the <hi>Croſſe</hi> with <hi>patience,</hi> and looſe <hi>all</hi> to find his God, deſerue's him not, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nùs te amat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>10.</hi> Conf. cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>qui tecum aliquid amat, quod non prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter te amat,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> Hee loue's thee <hi>little,</hi> who loue's any thing <hi>with thee,</hi> that hee doth not loue <hi>for thee;</hi> All this ſhadow and froth of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitorie things muſt vaniſh, for the hope of our bliſſe in future, <hi>Master we haue left all and followed thee</hi> (the <hi>Diſciples</hi> cry) <hi>What ſhall we haue?</hi> What ſhall yee haue? All things in hauing him, ſo ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyprian. de Coen. Dom.</note> 
               <hi>Cùm Dei ſint omnia, habenti Deum nil deerit, ſi ipſe Deo nòn deſit.</hi> Since all things are God's, to him that hath <hi>God,</hi> nothing can be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, except hee bee wanting vnto God; <hi>Nothing,</hi> ſaith the Father? <hi>No good thing,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, The young Lions doe lacke, and ſuffer hunger, but they that ſeeke the Lord ſhall want nothing that is good; Pſal.</hi> 34.10. Though all earthly perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions entrench thee, and <hi>Miſerie</hi> ſemes to come on like an <hi>Armed man;</hi> and thou art fallen into the iawes of thoſe enemie's, <hi>whoſe Teeth are Speares, and Arrowes, and their Tongue, a ſharpe Sword;</hi> yet Angels ſhall encampe about thee, and the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Hoaſts</hi> ſhall bee thy <hi>Buckler,</hi> and thy <hi>Shield;</hi> the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18643:14"/>
               <hi>Neighing of the Horſe, the Noiſe of the Trumpet</hi> ſhall not inuade thee; or if <hi>They</hi> doe, and at ſuch a ſtrait, that the <hi>Arme of Fleſh</hi> growe's weake, and all earthly fortification, vaine, yet <hi>his mercie is great vnto the Heauens, and his Truth reacheth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the cloudes; the glorious Hoaſt aboue ſhall muſter all their forces to aſsiſt thee, the Starres ſhall fight for thee, and Thunder ſpeake loud vnto thine enemies;</hi> Nay, <hi>God</hi> himſelfe ſhall vndertake thy quarrell, <hi>He ſhall bow the Heauens, and come downe; the Earth ſhall tremble, and the Foundations thereof ſhall ſhake becauſe Hee is angrie; Hee ſhall ſet his Terrours in Array, and fight mightily thy Battels, his ſeuere wrath he ſhall ſharpen as a ſword, and put on Ielouſie for compleate Armour; Loe, how hee breaketh the Bow in peeces, and Knappeth the Speare inſunder, and burneth the Chariots in the fire, Haileſtones full of furie he ſhoots as Arrowes, his right ayming thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolts goe abroad, and from the cloudes, as a well drawne Bow, they flye vnto the Marke.</hi> Thus in thy <hi>Height</hi> of miſeries, <hi>God</hi> ſhall bee thy <hi>Caſtle,</hi> and <hi>ſtrong Tower; and vnder the ſhadow of his wings ſhall be thy refuge, till theſe calamities be ouer-past. God</hi> neuer leaueth <hi>His,</hi> in their extremities; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>Caue,</hi> or in the <hi>Mountaine;</hi> in the <hi>Den,</hi> or in the <hi>Dungeon;</hi> he is alwayes there, both in his <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Aſsiſtance,</hi> and, ſometimes, in his <hi>Perſon,</hi> too; when all naturall ſupplies grow hopeleſſe, <hi>God</hi> purueye's for his children, by his <hi>Miracles; Rockes</hi> ſhall burſt with water; and <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens prouide Bread; and Cloudes drop fatneſſe;</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18643:15"/>
               <hi>Heauens ſhowre Manna;</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> adminiſter comforts; And at length. when all theſe <hi>whirle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winds,</hi> and <hi>fires</hi> and <hi>earthquakes</hi> of thy perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are gone by, <hi>God</hi> himſelfe ſhall ſpeake in the <hi>still voyce, Peace, peace vnto thee; Peace</hi> aſwell in thy <hi>outward,</hi> as <hi>inward</hi> ſtate; hee that hath giuen thee <hi>Ponerty, can</hi> giue thee <hi>Riches,</hi> and (vpon thy <hi>Sufferings</hi>) <hi>will;</hi> But when they come, take heed of that diſeaſe which commonly attend's thoſe which are riſen from a deſpis'd and meane <hi>condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> other goods giue onely <hi>greatnes</hi> of minde; <hi>Riches, inſolence.</hi> And therefore the <hi>Apostles</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice comes ſeaſonably heere, <hi>Be not high-minded,</hi> but <hi>feare,</hi> Feare, leaſt that God which beſtowed them on thee for thy <hi>Humiliation,</hi> will take them off againe for thy <hi>Pride;</hi> and ſo, when <hi>Riches</hi> come, put not thy <hi>truſt</hi> in them, and if they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, <hi>ſet not thy heart vpon them:</hi> that's the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part, the <hi>reſolution,</hi> or <hi>aduice</hi> giuen on the <hi>Caſe</hi> put, <hi>If Riches increaſe, ſet not thy heart vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin">Pars ſecunda.</note>Set not thy heart vpon them.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Rabbines,</hi> and <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> of old, attributed the whole <hi>Regiment</hi> of man to the <hi>Heart,</hi> and made that the <hi>Throne</hi> and chaire of the <hi>Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Soule;</hi> ſeating in it not onely the powers of <hi>vnderſtanding; Choice,</hi> but of <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Action</hi> too; So did the anncient <hi>Grecians;</hi> ſpecially, their <hi>Poets.</hi> The <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> on the other ſide, place them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18643:15"/>in the <hi>Braine;</hi> and leaue onely the <hi>Affections</hi> to the <hi>Heart;</hi> But, <hi>Diuinity</hi> is more bountifull, the <hi>Scripture</hi> giuing it the whole rationall power; <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, will, iudgement, conſultation, thought, endeauour;</hi> hence 'tis, that <hi>God</hi> ſo often ſcourge's the <hi>Hearts</hi> of men, commanding vs to <hi>confeſſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, loue,</hi> and feare him with all our heart; And therefore, <hi>that part</hi> is ſometimes taken for the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Soule;</hi> ſomtimes, for the <hi>whole</hi> man; Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the <hi>Prophet's Lacerate corda veſtra, Rent your Hearts, and not your garments;</hi> and <hi>This people ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour me with their lips, but their Heart is farre from mee;</hi> the <hi>Heart,</hi> the <hi>Shrine</hi> and <hi>Temple</hi> where I am truely worſhip'd; that <hi>Holocaust</hi> and <hi>Oblation</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which ſmoke's from this <hi>Altar,</hi> beare's the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable <hi>Odour;</hi> all other <hi>Sacrifices</hi> are abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the <hi>Heart</hi> is God's <hi>Iewell;</hi> hee doth appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate it to himſelfe, <hi>onely,</hi> and <hi>wholly;</hi> the <hi>hand,</hi> or <hi>foote,</hi> or <hi>eye</hi> are not forbidden to doe their office, both in <hi>gathering</hi> lawfully, and <hi>preſeruing</hi> riches; any member but the <hi>Heart</hi> may be thus employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that muſt not intermeddle, for this were to whore after a falſe <hi>Numen,</hi> and <hi>Burne Incenſe to a ſtrange God:</hi> 'Tis not the meere <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> or <hi>vſe</hi> of riches that offend's, but the <hi>Affectation;</hi> And to this purpoſe, <hi>Lumbard</hi> puts in his <hi>Obſeruation,</hi> with a <hi>non dicit Propheta,</hi> the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaye's not, <hi>nolite habere,</hi> but <hi>nolite cor opponere;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In koum.</note> wee are not forbidden riches; but when wee haue them, to ſet our <hi>Hearts</hi> vpon them; ſo that, the errour hang's not vpon <hi>thoſe,</hi> but <hi>vs;</hi> not on <hi>Riches,</hi> but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18643:16"/>that which <hi>Idoll's</hi> them, our <hi>Heart.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Moſes</hi> gaue a ſtong <hi>Caueat</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that when their <hi>Flocks</hi> and <hi>heards</hi> encreaſed, <hi>and their Siluer, and their Gold was multiplied, they ſhould beware leaſt their hearts were lifted vp, and ſo they ſhould forget the Lord their God. De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> 8.13.14. Thoſe ſublunarie creatures raiſe not <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction</hi> in vs, ſo wee make them not our <hi>Centre,</hi> if wee reſt not in them, if we can looke through them, to the <hi>Giuer;</hi> And, doubtles, wee may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine the vnrighteous <hi>Mammon,</hi> not onely as a <hi>Seruant,</hi> but a <hi>Friend,</hi> by no meanes, as a <hi>Lord.</hi> There is <hi>Vertue</hi> in the true vſe of it, if there be a <hi>Qualification</hi> in our <hi>deſires.</hi> And therefore, S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> diſputing of that impoſſible <hi>Analogie</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Heauen,</hi> and a <hi>Rich-man,</hi> a <hi>Camell,</hi> and the <hi>Eye of a Needle,</hi> would haue a <hi>Rich man</hi> vnderſtood there <hi>Cupidum rerum temporalium, &amp; de talibus ſuperbientem,</hi> ſuch a one, as ioynes <hi>Auarice</hi> to <hi>Riches,</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi> to <hi>Auarice,</hi> in his 2. Booke of <hi>Euang, quaeſt. Cap.</hi> 47. And this is the <hi>Burden</hi> of his Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation in three ſeuerall <hi>Tracts</hi> more, <hi>non opes damno ſed deſideria,</hi> in his 10. Sermon <hi>de tempore; non Diuitiae, ſed Cupiditas accuſatur,</hi> in his 5. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>de verbis Apoſtoli; in Diuitijs reprehendo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piditatem, non facultatem,</hi> in his firſt Booke <hi>de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Dei. Cap.</hi> 10. A moderate and timely care of <hi>neceſſary</hi> temporalls is not prohibited, but the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate</hi> Appetite is <hi>cryed-downe</hi> by the generall voyce and conſent both of <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> if you require a Catalogue; view more
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18643:16"/>punctually <hi>Gregory de Valentia</hi> vpon <hi>Aquinas</hi> 2.2.3. <hi>Tome</hi> 4. diſputation, 5. queſtion. Hereupon,<note place="margin">Sen. de Beat. vit.</note> the <hi>Moraliſts,</hi> and thoſe of rigid and ſeuerer <hi>Brow,</hi> would haue a <hi>wiſe man</hi> paſſe by <hi>Riches,</hi> in <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, Nonne habeat, ſed ne ſolicitus habeat,</hi> not in regard of their <hi>propricty,</hi> and <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> but the <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty</hi> and <hi>eagerneſſe</hi> of the <hi>purſuit;</hi> which as hee can manage without <hi>Indulgence,</hi> in their <hi>fruition;</hi> ſo, without <hi>diſturbance,</hi> in their <hi>loſſe;</hi> In what ſtore-houſe may <hi>Fortune</hi> better locke vp her <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> then there, from whence ſhee may fetch it without the complaint of him that keepes it? <hi>M. Cato,</hi> when he praiſed <hi>Curius</hi> and <hi>Caruncani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and the <hi>voluntary</hi> and <hi>affected pouertie</hi> of that <hi>Age,</hi> wherein it was a Capitall offence to haue ſome few plates of <hi>Siluer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sen. Epiſt. <hi>119.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Poſſidebat ipſe quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies ſeſtertium,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> had his owne ſtore cram'd with many a <hi>Seſterce.</hi> A wiſe man, as hee will not make <hi>Riches</hi> the <hi>Object</hi> of his purſuite, ſo not, of his <hi>refuſall, non amat Diuitias, ſed mauult; non in animam illam gazam ſed in domum recipit; nec reſpuit poſſeſſas Diuitias, ſed contemnit;</hi> 'tis <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca's</hi> againe, to his <hi>Iunius Gallio,</hi> hee weigh's them ſo euenly betweene, <hi>Deſire,</hi> and <hi>Scorne,</hi> that hee doth neither <hi>vnder-valew,</hi> nor <hi>indulge</hi> them; hee make's not his <hi>minde,</hi> their <hi>Magazine,</hi> but his <hi>Houſe,</hi> in which he doth not <hi>locke</hi> but <hi>lodge</hi> them; he loue's them not, properly, but by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, not as they are <hi>riches,</hi> but as they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loofe from <hi>Pouerty:</hi> Yes, Stoicke,<note place="margin">Sen. de Beat, vit. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> as they are <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> they may not onely be temperately lou'd and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18643:17"/>deſir'd, but alſo prayed for, prayed for as our <hi>dayly bread;</hi> not abſolutely, as for our ſpirituall improue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but by way of <hi>reſtriction;</hi> firſt humbly, with ſubmiſſion to the will of God; then, <hi>conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,</hi> ſo they proue aduantagious either to our <hi>ciuill</hi> or <hi>morall</hi> good. But here wee muſt warily ſteeere betweene a vigilant prouidence, and a fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſolicitude, a diſcreete and honeſt care, and that which is anxious, and intemperate; for if they are purſued either with <hi>vnlawfull,</hi> or <hi>vnbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled</hi> deſire; they leade our <hi>Reaſon</hi> captiue, <hi>Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold</hi> our <hi>Intellectuals,</hi> ſtartle and diſturbe our ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, and better thoughts, weane our <hi>Cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> from <hi>Sacred</hi> proiect to matters of <hi>Secular</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, ſteale from vs the exerciſe of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all duties, and ſo damp and dead all the faculties of the <hi>Inward man,</hi> that in way of <hi>Conſcience</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> we are benum'd meerely; <hi>Naball</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe not ſo <hi>ſtony</hi> and <hi>churliſh,</hi> not halfe ſo <hi>ſupine</hi> and ſtupified as we. And therefore, your earthly <hi>Senſualiſts</hi> haue this wofull <hi>brand</hi> ſet vpon them by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God. <hi>They are men of this world, they haue their portion in this life onely. Pſal.</hi> 17.14. <hi>Riches</hi> haue nothing ſubſtantiall in them that may allure vs, but our cuſtome of admiring them, <hi>Non quia concupiſcenda ſunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sen Ep. <hi>119.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>lau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>antur; ſed quià concupiſcuntur, laudata ſunt,</hi> They are not praiſed, becauſe they are to be deſired, but they are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red becauſe they are prayſed. To cut out our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires by weake preſidents is at once <hi>folly</hi> and <hi>mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> 'tis miſerable to follow <hi>error</hi> by <hi>example;</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:18643:17"/>That this man hugg's his <hi>Mammon,</hi> is no authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for my Auarice; I muſt chalke out my procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings by the line of precept, ſquare them by the rules of Diuine truth; and that tel's mee <hi>Riches</hi> are but <hi>ſnares, thornes, vanities, ſhadowes, nothing.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim 6.9. Math. 13.22.</note> Wilt thou ſet thine eyes vpon that <hi>which is not?</hi> ſaith the <hi>Wiſe man;</hi> For certainly, <hi>Riches make themſelues wings, they flye away as an Eagle towards heauen, Pro.</hi> 18. Marke, all their pompe is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>certainty,</hi> or <hi>ſtation:</hi> Things not onely <hi>fleeting,</hi> but <hi>voluble;</hi> they <hi>ſteale</hi> not from vs, but they <hi>flye</hi> away; flye away as an <hi>Eagle</hi> doth, both with ſtrong, and nimble wing; Their <hi>Ebbe</hi> is as ſodaine, as their <hi>flowe</hi> doubtfull; the <hi>Text</hi> onely preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the one, with a <hi>ſi affiuxerint, if</hi> they flow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thee, as if their increaſe were meerely <hi>caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all:</hi> But if they doe, what then? <hi>Nolite cor oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere,</hi> ſet not your heart vpon them; They are <hi>tranſitory obiects,</hi> they flye away, not only with the pinions of an <hi>Eagle,</hi> but with the wings of a <hi>Doue,</hi> of the <hi>Doue,</hi> in the <hi>Pſalmiſt, whoſe wings were couered with ſiluer, and her feathers with gold. Riches</hi> (I confeſſe) haue their <hi>Beauty,</hi> and <hi>luſtre;</hi> but they are falſe, like globes of <hi>Chriſtall,</hi> which though they take the eye both with varietie and delight of <hi>Obiects,</hi> yet haue of themſelues but a hollow and brittle glory, <hi>nihil ex his quae videmus manet, currit cum tempore:</hi> Winds and Seas are not ſo roling and vnſtable as <hi>Riches</hi> are, when they begin to ſurge and ſwell the <hi>Heart, that is ſet vpon them: vides quia fluunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ambroſ. ad Mamm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>non vides quiapraeter flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18643:18"/>
                     <hi>fluenta ſunt quae miraris, quomodò veniunt, ſic tranſeunt, et recedunt vt diſcas ſuperflua non acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere,</hi> Loe, how the Father, playing on the word, chide's his folly, and opening the ſtickle condition of theſe ſliding Temporalls, prohibite's all deſire of vnneceſſary Treaſure, to ſweate after <hi>ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and vaine Abundance, ſince the way to them is both ſteepe, and ſlippery, and like the climbing of a ſandie hill to the feete of the Aged. No man can be poſſeſſed of a peaceable and quiet life that toyle's much about the inlargement of it. <hi>Seneca's habere quod neceſſe eſt, &amp; quod ſat eſt,</hi> may well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat all <hi>earthly happines,</hi> and terminate our deſires in way of riches, to haue that which is neceſſary, &amp; that which is ſufficient; But this latter we muſt bound againe with the rules of <hi>Nature,</hi> not <hi>opinion.</hi> The <hi>Epicure</hi> tels vs, <hi>If we liue according to Nature, we ſhall neuer be poore; if, according to opinion, neuer rich.</hi> Our naturall deſires haue their liſts,</hi> and Bounds; Thoſe that are deriued from falſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, haue no pale; to him that goeth in a right way there is an end; <hi>Error</hi> is infinite. As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there are diuers ſorts of <hi>Riches,</hi> ſo there are of <hi>Deſires,</hi> too; there are <hi>Riches naturall,</hi> and there are <hi>Riches Artificiall;</hi> there are <hi>Deſires</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> and there are <hi>Deſires</hi> of <hi>Choice. Naturall Riches,</hi> ſuch as are ſurrogated to man for the ſupply of naturall defects; as <hi>meate, drinke, clothing; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall;</hi> by which <hi>Nature</hi> is not immediately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued, but by way of <hi>conſequence,</hi> as <hi>Coyne, Plate, Iewels,</hi> and the like, which the <hi>Art</hi> of man firſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18643:18"/>found out for eaſier trafficke and exchange; or (as the vnhewed language of the <hi>Schoole. man</hi> rough's it) <hi>propter menſuram rerum venalium.</hi> Now na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall deſires ſhake hands with naturall Riches; they are not infinite, but haue their meaſure, and growth, and proportion with the other. Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Riches are without period, and come vp to thoſe defires of <hi>Choice;</hi> which becauſe inordinate, and not modified; are noe leſſe then infinite. <hi>Hee that drinke's of this water</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls) <hi>ſhall thirſt againe, Ioh.</hi> 4. The Reaſon is, becauſe their inſufficiencie is moſt knowen when they are had, and therefore diſcouer's their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection more; ſo that <hi>Naturall Riches</hi> are more exquiſite becauſe they haue naturall <hi>deſires</hi> which are infinite; The other not without <hi>Confuſion</hi> and <hi>Diſorder,</hi> becauſe their deſires depend on <hi>Choice,</hi> which are mutable and various; and ſo, <hi>Infinite.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aquin. ſeeunda ſecundae, q. <hi>1.</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi> ad ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum. <hi>Cato.</hi>
                  </note> That <hi>Rigid cenſor</hi> of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> was both <hi>Home,</hi> and witty, to the ſupefluous vanities of his time, <hi>Any thing will ſuffice, if what we want we require of our ſelues;</hi> hee that ſeeke's for content, <hi>without him,</hi> looſeth both <hi>himſelfe,</hi> and <hi>it;</hi> not to <hi>deſire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">vis fieri diues Pentifice? nii cupias <hi>Mart,</hi> Sert Epiſt. <hi>119.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>haue,</hi> are of a nere <hi>Bloud - Quare igitur a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna potius impetrem, vt det, quam a me, ne petam?</hi> ſaith the <hi>Stoicke, Why ſhould I rather deſire of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, that ſhe would giue mee? then of my ſelfe that I would not deſire? Riches</hi> haue nothing ſolid in them; for if they had, they would ſometimes ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>fill</hi> or <hi>pleaſe</hi> vs; but they play with our <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites</hi> as the <hi>apples</hi> did with the lips of <hi>Tantalus,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:18643:19"/>which he might <hi>kiſſe,</hi> not <hi>Taſte;</hi> or, ſuppoſe, <hi>Taſt</hi> them, 'tis but as water to one ſicke of a violent <hi>fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,</hi> now drinking eagerly to allay his thirſt, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larges it; and ſeeking ſomething to coole his Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he enflame's them. Wee are neuer <hi>in</hi> our ſelues, but <hi>beyond; Feare,</hi> or <hi>Deſire,</hi> or <hi>Hope</hi> draw vs euer to that which is <hi>to come,</hi> and remoue our ſence and conſideration from that <hi>which is,</hi> to muſe on that which <hi>ſhall be,</hi> euen when wee <hi>ſhall be no more. Inuentus eſt, qui concupiſceret Aliquid poſt omnia.</hi> There are ſome, that hauing <hi>all things,</hi> haue (notwithſtanding) coueted <hi>ſomewhat;</hi> like wide mouth'd <hi>Glaſſes</hi> brimb'd vp with rich <hi>Elix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars;</hi> put <hi>gold</hi> in them, They are ne're the fuller; And this is a puniſhment euer waites vpon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled, and immoderate <hi>Appetites, Hee that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſiluer, ſhall not bee ſatisfied with ſiluer, nor hee that loueth Abundance, with increaſe, Eccle.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Miſerable Deſires,</hi> haue <hi>miſerable effects;</hi> They degrade and deueſt <hi>Man</hi> of that preheminence he hath aboue other Creatures, and bring him down to <hi>Beaſts;</hi> nay, vnder them; For they hauing quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched their <hi>Deſires,</hi> by their <hi>Fruition,</hi> remaine fully ſatisfied, till <hi>Nature</hi> quicken againe their <hi>Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites,</hi> like plants in a fat ſoyle, which neuer require ſhewers, but in drought; thoſe of <hi>Man</hi> are euer <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenous</hi> and <hi>inſatiate,</hi> like barren &amp; thirſty ground, which euen <hi>then</hi> lacks <hi>moiſture,</hi> when <hi>ouer flowed.</hi> Thoughts which ſtreame towards <hi>wealth,</hi> or <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> haue no certaine <hi>channell;</hi> but, like a <hi>Torrent</hi> or full tide, either beate downe or elſe ouer-runne
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18643:19"/>their bankes. There was neuer <hi>Mammoniſt,</hi> whoſe <hi>Exceſſe</hi> of Treaſure, or <hi>Extent</hi> of Fortune, could limit his <hi>Concupiſcence;</hi> but it might well riuall the <hi>Ambition</hi> of thoſe <hi>Proud Kings</hi> of old, who not ſatisfied with the <hi>Glory</hi> of their owne Crownes, and hauing nothing more on earth to bee deſired, would counterfaite the <hi>Lightning</hi> and <hi>Thunder,</hi> to haue themſelues thought <hi>powerfull</hi> in <hi>Heauen</hi> alſo, make him <hi>Lord</hi> of the whole <hi>Earth;</hi> giue him her Mynes of Gold, Coaſts of <hi>Iaſper,</hi> Rocks of <hi>Diamonds;</hi> nay, all the Treaſure the wombe of the Earth, or bowels of the great Deepe haue ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; yet, euen in theſe flouds, hee thirſteth, in this ſurfet, he is hungry, in theſe <hi>Riches,</hi> poore. O the <hi>Inexhauſtedneſſe of Humane Appetite. Quod naturae ſatì; eſt, Homini nòn eſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sen Epiſt. <hi>119.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nature</hi> hath not in her vaſt ſtore-houſe wherewith to ſupply our bottomleſſe Deſires; thoſe Deſires, I meane, which attend our <hi>Choice;</hi> For as they depend on the Imaginations of men (which are <hi>fertile,</hi> and euer blooming) as <hi>this Power</hi> repreſent's the formes and Images of infinite <hi>Obiects,</hi> ſo our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires multiply ſtrangely to purſue all thoſe things the Imagination hath propounded; inſomuch, that we proſecute them (oftentimes) without <hi>Rule,</hi> or <hi>Meaſure,</hi> and there is ſooner an end of <hi>vs,</hi> then of our <hi>Couetouſnes.</hi> I know there are <hi>Deſires</hi> Innocent enough, if they had their Bounds; But their <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe,</hi> and <hi>Reſtleſneſſe,</hi> doth blemiſh their purſuite; the <hi>Chryſolite,</hi> the <hi>Berill,</hi> and the <hi>Saphire,</hi> and all the ſparkling, and ſhelly <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> of <hi>Pearle,</hi> and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18643:20"/>
                  <hi>Stone,</hi> are the <hi>Obiects</hi> of a harmeleſſe delight, if we could vſe them moderately; But, we ſuffer our ſelues to be tranſported with ſuch violent Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and we ſeeke them with ſuch enraged heate, that 'tis rather <hi>Madneſſe,</hi> then <hi>Deſire;</hi> Nay, of all humane <hi>Aſpirations</hi> there are none ſo <hi>lawleſſe,</hi> and <hi>Exorbitant,</hi> as thoſe which wander after <hi>Riches;</hi> For whereas the Reſt aime only at the <hi>Ioy</hi> and <hi>Content</hi> which may arriue them by the poſſeſſion of their <hi>Obiects,</hi> and ſo, <hi>lull,</hi> and <hi>ſtumber,</hi> (like two loude and ſteepe <hi>Currents,</hi> which meeting in a Flat kiſſe, &amp; are ſilent.) Thoſe of <hi>Riche,</hi> grow more <hi>violent,</hi> by Abundance, like the flame of a great fire, which increaſeth by cafting wood into it. There can be no true <hi>Riches,</hi> without <hi>Content;</hi> and there can be no true content where there is ſtill a <hi>Deſire</hi> of riches; will you haue the Reaſon? the <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt</hi> giue's it,<note place="margin">Sen. Epiſt. <hi>112.</hi>
                  </note> but not home, <hi>Plùs incipit habere poſſe, qui plùs habet,</hi> Hee that hath much, begin's to haue a poſſibilitie, to haue more; and thus, as our <hi>Heapes</hi> are inlarged, ſo are our <hi>Affections,</hi> and <hi>They</hi> once <hi>Inordinate,</hi> the <hi>Heart</hi> is inſtantly rent aſunder with the whirle-winds and diſtempers of various <hi>luſts;</hi> ſometimes, it hunt's for <hi>Treaſure,</hi> ſometimes for <hi>Henours</hi> and <hi>Preferment,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing gotten the poſſeſſion of theſe, ſtill fight's a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her owne Satisfaction by deſiring more; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that if we could empty the <hi>Weſterne Parts</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> and the <hi>Eaſt</hi> of all her <hi>Spices;</hi> the <hi>Land</hi> of her vndig'd, and the <hi>Sea</hi> of her <hi>ſhipwrack't</hi> ſtore; if we could lay on our <hi>Maſſe</hi> to the very <hi>Starres;</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:18643:20"/>yet <hi>Deſire is as woman, and the Graue, as Death and Hell,</hi> which will not bee ſatisfied. Such are the reſtleſſe wandrings of our Affections, ſet once on <hi>Temporalls,</hi> that They ſinde nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Banke, nor Bottome; there is no reſt to man's Soule, but in God's Eternall Reſt; for there being no proportion betweene <hi>Spirits,</hi> and <hi>Bodies;</hi> 'tis impoſſible that the infinite deſires of the Soule ſhould be confin'd to <hi>Creatures</hi> heere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, as <hi>Things</hi> too <hi>Languiſhing,</hi> and <hi>Tranſitorie,</hi> for ſuch Diuine Subſtances to reſide in, with full ſatisfaction, or finall Reſt: The heart of man, not fixt in the contemplation of <hi>Eternitie,</hi> is alwayes erraticke, and <hi>vnſtable, Et omni volubilitate vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubilius</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) more voluble then vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubilitie it ſelfe; It trauel's from one <hi>Obiect</hi> to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſeeking reſt where there is none; but in thoſe fraile and fleeting Temporals, in which, our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are (as 'twere) ſhackled, and let bound, It ſhall neuer find any <hi>Laſting</hi> and true <hi>Content;</hi> For our <hi>Soule</hi> is of that vaſt comprehenſiueneſſe, and our <hi>Deſire</hi> of that wilde <hi>Latitude,</hi> and <hi>Extent,</hi> that no Finite <hi>Excellencie</hi> or <hi>Created Comfort,</hi> can euer fill it, but it is ſtill tortut'd on the <hi>Racke</hi> of <hi>restleſſe Diſcontent,</hi> and <hi>Selfe-vexation,</hi> vntill it faſten vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an <hi>Obiect,</hi> infinite, both in <hi>Endleſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection;</hi> only admit it to the Face of <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificall Viſion,</hi> and ſo conſequently to thoſe Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of pleaſure, and fulnes of <hi>Ioy</hi> flowing thence; and then preſently (and neuer till then) It's infinite defire expire's in the <hi>Boſome</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and lie's
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18643:21"/>downe ſoftly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bolt.</hi> walke with God, <hi>pag.</hi> 125.</note> with ſweeteſt peace, and full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, in the embracements of <hi>euerlaſting Bliſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, <hi>O Earth, Earth, Earth, heare the Word of the Lord.</hi> Thou whoſe <hi>Bodie</hi> and <hi>Soule,</hi> and <hi>Deſires</hi> are lumpiſh, <hi>Earth</hi> meerely, thrice <hi>Earth;</hi> Raiſe thine <hi>Affections</hi> from this Dull <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> where they now grouell, and <hi>looke vp to the Hils from whence thy ſaluation commeth:</hi> why do they flutter heere about corruptible <hi>Glories?</hi> Why doe they ſtoope to falſe and vaine <hi>Comforts,</hi> ſuch as are not only open to <hi>Caſualtie,</hi> but to <hi>Danger? Riches</hi> are to <hi>Both?</hi> to <hi>Both,</hi> in a triple way; Firſt, in their <hi>Acquiſition,</hi> Secondly, <hi>Poſſeſsion,</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Depriuation.</hi> In their <hi>Acquiſition,</hi> firſt; <hi>As the Partridge ſitteth on egges, and hatcheth them not;</hi> ſo <hi>He that getteth Riches, and not by right, ſhall leaue them in the midſt of his Age, and at his End bee a foole. Ier.</hi> 17.11. Next in their <hi>Poſſeſsion, where Moth and ruſt doth corrupt them, and where Theeues breake through, and ſteale, Math.</hi> 6.9. Laſtly, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their <hi>Depriuation,</hi> or <hi>Loſſe. He hath ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed downe Riches,</hi> and <hi>Hee ſhall vomit them vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; God ſhall caſt them out of his Belly; the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of his houſe ſhall depart, and his goods ſhall flow away in the day of his wrath, Iob</hi> 20.15, 28. <hi>Loe,</hi> how the <hi>Hand</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> houers heere, and with a Double Blow ſtrike's through the very Ioynts and marrow of the <hi>Worlaling,</hi> euen to the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring and diſſipation both of his <hi>Poſteritie</hi> and <hi>Fortunes? His goods ſhall flow away, and the Increaſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18643:21"/>of his houſe ſhall depart; ſhall depart?</hi> whither? <hi>to the Graue;</hi> with whom? <hi>(two lamentable Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.) The Foole and the Beaſt that periſheth.</hi> So ſaith the <hi>Singer</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in his 49. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> thrice in that one <hi>Pſalme,</hi> at the ſixth verſe, <hi>He truſt's in his wealth, and glorie's in the multitude of his Riches,</hi> and at the tenth Verſe, <hi>He is a foole, and brutiſh, and leaueth his goods to others. O vaine Inſolence? O tranſitorie height?</hi> what? After all thoſe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings and ſwarmes of <hi>Treaſure,</hi> muſt he leaue his <hi>Substance</hi> to Others? Yea, to others, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, neither of his <hi>Tribe,</hi> nor <hi>Countrey.</hi> Pleaſe you to looke vpon him at the eleuenth Verſe, his very heart is tranſparent, and you may diſcouer his inward thoughts. <hi>Hee conceiue's his houſe ſhall contìnue for euer, and his Dwelling place to all gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and therefore cals his Lands after his owne Name;</hi> yet view him againe at the fourteenth Verſe. <hi>He is a Beaſt, a ſilly one, a ſheepe laid in the graue, Death ſhall feed vpon him, and the vpright ſhall haue Dominion ouer him in the morning, and his ſtrength ſhall conſume in the pit from his Dwelling place.</hi> Once more, He is twice in that <hi>Pſalme</hi> ſtil'd <hi>A Man of Honour,</hi> but 'tis ſauc'd with a <hi>Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, He abideth not,</hi> at the twelfth Verſe; and <hi>He vnder ſtandeth not,</hi> at the twentieth Verſe; and in both, <hi>He is a Beaſt that periſheth.</hi> Marke, how the Spirit of God paint's out this very <hi>Earth-worme,</hi> this great <hi>Monopoliſt</hi> of pelfe, and Rubbiſh. <hi>He is ignorant, Tranſitorie, Senſuall; He abideth not, hee
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18643:22"/>vnder ſtandeth not, and (anon) he dieth;</hi> Dieth? no, <hi>periſheth; periſheth as a Beaſt doth,</hi> as if the <hi>Soule</hi> rotted with the <hi>Body,</hi> or his <hi>Memory</hi> with the <hi>Soule;</hi> no Remainder either of <hi>Name,</hi> or <hi>Fortune,</hi> and which is worſt, of <hi>Honour;</hi> ſo ſaith the Text; <hi>What though rich; and the Glory of his houſe increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed?</hi> yet, <hi>He ſhall carry away nothing with him, his Honour ſhall not deſcendafter him, verſe</hi> 17. what? carry nothing away with him? not that <hi>Glorious Earth? that Gaudy Luggage</hi> his Soule Doted on? that <hi>ſhining Saint?</hi> that <hi>Burniſh'd Deity,</hi> which he could, at once, both touch and <hi>worſhip?</hi> what? not the <hi>Cabonet</hi> he <hi>hug'd</hi> and <hi>claſp'd?</hi> not the <hi>Gold</hi> hee <hi>Idol'd?</hi> nothing of <hi>Treaſure,</hi> or <hi>Repute,</hi> or <hi>Name?</hi> Of neither; All theſe falſe beames which were wont to dazle him ſhall bee now clouded in perpetuall darkneſſe, where they ſhall neuer ſee light againe; thus the Text doome's him, at the nineteenth Verſe of the ſame <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing then, All earthly Dependences are vaine and fragile, and there can be no true peace but that which looke's vpward; Take for Concluſion the aduice of <hi>Siracides, Lay vp Treaſures according to the Commandement of the moſt High; and they ſhall bring thee more profit then gold;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eeclus 39.</note> 
                  <hi>Treaſures of the moſt high?</hi> What are Theſe? How laid vp? and where? The <hi>Commandement</hi> of the moſt <hi>High</hi> tell's thee, <hi>Lay vp for your ſelues Treaſures in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, Bags which waxe not old, the good foundation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the time to come, the hold of eternall life, the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18643:22"/>Euerlaſting Memoriall before God;</hi> that <hi>Treaſure</hi> which the <hi>Angell</hi> ſhewed <hi>Cornelius</hi> in the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; euen thine <hi>Almes,</hi> and thy <hi>Prayers;</hi> not thy <hi>large-lung'd Prayers,</hi> without <hi>Almes,</hi> ſuch as the old <hi>Phariſee</hi> bleated in his <hi>Synagogue,</hi> or the <hi>New one,</hi> in his <hi>Conuenticle;</hi> but thine <hi>Almes,</hi> and thy <hi>Prayers,</hi> hand in hand, with one cheerefulneſſe, and <hi>Truth;</hi> thy <hi>hearty Zeale</hi> towards <hi>God,</hi> and thy <hi>willing Charity</hi> towards <hi>Man,</hi> and both theſe, in ſecret, and without noiſe. Such, and only ſuch, are <hi>Golden Vialls</hi> full of <hi>Odours, ſweet Incenſe</hi> in the <hi>Nostrils</hi> of the <hi>Almighty;</hi> They ſhall yeeld a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſmell, as the <hi>Best Myrrhe,</hi> as <hi>Galbanum,</hi> and <hi>Onyx and ſweet Storax, and as the fume of Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe in the Tabernacle.</hi> Heere are <hi>Treaſures</hi> which neuer faile, where no <hi>Moth</hi> corrupteth, nor <hi>Thiefe</hi> approcheth; theſe ſhall fight for thee againſt thine <hi>Enemies,</hi> better then a <hi>mighty ſhield, or a ſtrong ſpeare.</hi> If thou breake the <hi>Staffe</hi> of thy <hi>Bread</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hungry, and afflicted, <hi>God ſhall make fat thy Bones, and ſatisfie thy Soule in Drought; Thou ſhalt be like awatred Garden, and like a ſpring whoſe ſtreames faile not; Treaſures thou ſhalt lay vp as Dust, and Gold of Ophir, as the ſtones of the Brooke; Thy Paſtures ſhall be cloth'd with flockes, the Valleys alſo ſhall ſtand ſo thicke with Corne, that they ſhall laugh, and ſing;</hi> In ſine; <hi>Thou ſhalt take root in an honourable place, euen in the portion of the Lord's Inheritance, when thou ſhalt be exalted as a Cypreſſe tree vpon the Mountaines of Hermon, like a Palme tree in Engedy, and as a Roſe plant in Iericho:</hi> And, at
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18643:23"/>length, when the <hi>Glory</hi> of thoſe <hi>Earthly Manſions</hi> muſt bee left, when thou canſt bee no longer <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> but art to paſſe thy ſtrict Account before the <hi>Great Houſe-holder</hi> at the <hi>Generall and Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Audit,</hi> when the Booke of all our Actions ſhall be vnclaps'd, thine ſhall be found <hi>ſquare,</hi> and <hi>euen,</hi> and thou ſhalt receiue that happie <hi>Applauſe,</hi> and <hi>Remuneration, Well done, thou good, and faithfull Seruant, Enter into thy Maſters Ioy.</hi> Which the <hi>Lord</hi> grant for <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> ſake,</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
               <closer>Gloria in excelſis Deo.</closer>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <l>Rode caper vites, tamen hic eum ſtabis ad Aras,</l>
                     <l>In tua quod fundi cornua poſſit, erit.</l>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:18643:23"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
